Abraham: So, what are the consequences and
implications of inadequate cyber security?
Nicole: Cyber security should
be one of the top priorities in
all companies large or small,
as the sophistication and the
number of threats is increasing.
Data is the lifeblood of most
organisations and is the key component
of day-to-day operations, therefore
security breaches that lead to the
loss of data can be catastrophic.
Companies and organisations need
a security strategy to cover
networks, servers, workstations,
cloud, applications, and data.
Abraham: Not taking cyber
security seriously can lead to
irreparable reputational damage,
fines, and issues with licensing
in case of regulated businesses.
It can also cause adverse media
coverage, increased anxiety and stress
levels in employees and problems
related to areas such as GDPR.
So, let’s look in a little more
detail at what the consequences
of an attack could be.
Nicole: Operational Disruptions-
Ransomware can lead to hackers
holding a company to ransom by
infiltrating and accessing their
system, and its core datasets, and
then asking for money, or else!
This can lead to the shutting down of
the company’s entire IT infrastructure
and business critical systems, to isolate
the damage, investigate and recover.
For companies that do not have a
recovery plan or back-ups in place, it
may take weeks or months to get back
to where they were before the attack.
This can cause disruptions to business
operations, have a negative impact on
productivity, causing customers to go
elsewhere, resulting in a loss of revenue.
Abraham: Legal Ramifications
Data breaches involving customer’s and
commercial partner’s personal information,
can lead to lawsuits against the company.
These can have the impact of lowering
trust and confidence, and may involve
hefty fines from regulatory bodies,
legal fees and expensive court cases.
In case of regulated businesses, the
authorities may even restrict companies
from carrying certain operations until
legal investigations are concluded,
to see how an attack could take place,
and to make sure it won’t happen again.
Nicole: Financial loss
All cyber criminal acts, whether
direct or indirect, can have
a negative financial impact.
Loss of business, legal fees, fines,
cost of containing an attack or
breach, compensation pay-outs, and a
potential reduction in share price.
Data breaches especially, can be hard
for a business to overcome and renew
trust in former clients and give
confidence to new ones, therefore making
it possible for companies to go under.
Some businesses have a
‘never-going-to-happen-to-me’ attitude
towards cyber security and have inadequate
security measures in place in general.
But in this day and age, everyone should
air on the side of caution and change that
attitude to ‘it could easily happen to me!